Finding aid for the Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy records, 1987-2013 LSC.2252
UCLA Library Special Collections
Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy records
1987-2013
1996-2006
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2252
29.8 Linear Feet (7 boxes, 27 cartons, and 1 flat box)
The Tourism Industry Development Council (TIDC), later changed to Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE), was founded in 1993 by Maria Elena Durazo, then president of Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees (HERE) Local 11, Tom Walsh, HERE Local 814, Father Dick Gillette, Episcopal Church, Kent Wong, UCLA Labor Center, and Madeline Janis-Aparicio, Executive Director, to address conditions in the Los Angeles tourism industry, a large generator of low wage jobs and poverty in Los Angeles. The collection consists of correspondence, LAANE campaign ephemera, an extensive press clippings files representing LAANE activities and/or events of tangential interest to the organization, photographs, a small amount of files documenting administrative activities, and a small number of fundraising event publications and programs and reports and research prepared by/for LAANE.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital and audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7780072
History
The Tourism Industry Development Council (TIDC), later renamed Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE), was founded in 1993 by Maria Elena Durazo, then president of Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees (HERE) Local 11, Tom Walsh HERE Local 814, Father Dick Gillette, Episcopal Church, Kent Wong, UCLA Labor Center, and Madeline Janis-Aparicio, Executive Director, to address conditions in the L.A. tourism industry, a major generator of low wage employment and poverty. Their original mission was to improve job quality in the Los Angeles tourism industry and attract tourist to non-traditional destinations of interest.
Over the years LAANE has been involved in a number of social justice campaigns which have helped to bring about social and economic change in the greater Los Angeles area. In 1995, TIDC proposed and the Los Angeles City Council passed a Worker Retention Ordinance, which provides airport concession workers (and other employees of city contractors) the opportunity to remain in their jobs as new companies take over airport contracts such as restaurants and retail stores. In 1996, they facilitated the creation of Clergy and Laity United for Economic Justice (CLUE) to engage religious leaders to support low wage workers throughout California.
Also in 1996, TIDC led a movement for a Los Angeles Living Wage Ordinance covering workers employed, contracted with, or receiving subsidies from the city of Los Angeles or its agencies and leasees. During this time, TIDC adopted its new name, Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy, to reflect its expanding mission. Following the implementation of Los Angeles Living Wage Ordinance, LAANE began Respect at LAX to ensure enforcement of the ordinance. From 1996 to 2002, LAANE organized Santa Monicans Allied for Responsible Tourism (SMART) to partner with hotel workers in an attempt to create a living wage law in Santa Monica. In the late 1990s and onward, LAANE won a dozen Community Benefit Agreements (CBAs) for development projects including the Staples Center expansion (L.A. Live) and the Hollywood and Vine project. In 2004, LAANE built a community coalition to fight a Walmart-Sponsored Ballot Initiative to build a superstore in Inglewood. In 2005, LAANE began Coalition for a New Century, extending the Living Wage Ordinance and Tip Protection Ordinance to 2,000 workers in 13 hotels on Century Boulevard, adjacent to the LAX airport.
In 2012, LAANE's Long Beach Coalition for Good Jobs and Healthy Communities saw the passing of a ballot measure mandating living wages and tip protection for 2,000 workers at the city's large hotels. Additionally, during this time LAANE focused on environmental issues through their campaigns Don't Waste L.A. and Repower L.A. Also in 2012, they were involved with the Construction Careers Policy adopted by the County Metropolitan Transit Authority, the Port of L.A. and the City's Department of Public Works to guarantee career jobs and training to low-income, people of color, women and other community members. LAANE's first national effort, the Jobs to Move America campaign sought to improve transit systems and create and retain stable jobs in the manufacturing sector.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of files related to the social justice organization, Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (LAANE). The files document a number of LAANE's campaign efforts related to living wage in the Los Angeles and Santa Monica area including Worker Retention Ordinance, Living Wage Ordinance, and Santa Monica Living Wage among others. Individual files may include one or more of the following: correspondence, campaign ephemera, and occasional clippings, notes, research, and publications. Additionally included are photographs, original and photocopied press clippings representing LAANE activities and/or events of tangential interest to the organization, a small amount of files documenting administrative activities, and a small number of fundraising event publications and programs, and reports and research prepared by/for LAANE. Notably absent from the collection are materials documenting LAANE's Long Beach Coalition for Good Jobs and Healthy Communities, environmental campaigns, and Construction Careers Policy.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Campaign Files
Madeline Janis Files
Vivian Rothstein Files
Administrative Activities
Foundation Proposals and Reports
Fundraising Events Publications and Programs
Reports and Research
Alliances with Others
Press Clippings
Photographs and Ephemera
Distributive justice -- Archives; Los Angeles Alliance for a New Economy (Organization) -- Archives
- Campaign Files, 1990-circa 2003
  Related Material
  A small number of items related to Respect at LAX can be found in the Service Employees International Union, United Service Workers West Records (Collection 1940). UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
  Scope and Content
  The series consists of materials documenting various LAANE campaigns, over the first 10 years of the organization's work. Included among the files are one or more of the following: correspondence, campaign ephemera, and occasional clippings, notes, research, and publications. Additionally included are small number of videos, DVDs and audio cassettes of LAANE and/or media created coverage of LAANE activities. The bulk of the files represent Los Angeles Living Wage, Respect at LAX (to raise the standards of the jobs at L.A. Airport), and Santa Monica Living Wage campaigns. Additional represented campaigns include Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood, Community Benefits Agreements, Community Redevelopment Agency policies, Health Coverage, and Subsidy Policy 2000. Notably absent from the series are materials documenting LAANE's subsequent Long Beach Coalition for Good Jobs and Healthy Communities, Clean Trucks Program, Repower L.A., and Construction Careers Policy. The series is arranged alphabetically by campaign name. See also the Press Clippings, the Photographs and Ephemera, the Madeline Janis Files and the Vivian Rothstein Files series for possible materials related to LAANE Campaigns.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  THE SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, please notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Clean and Safe Ports
    - Clean Air, Good Jobs, and Safe Ports (DVD recording), (undated) (Box 28)
      Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, please notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood
    - Casino Surveys, (1995) (Box 12)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) (2 files), (1996-1998) (Box 20)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) address list, (undated) (Box 20)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) Analysis of Stadium EIR (Environmental Impact Report), (circa 1995) (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) Correspondence with Hollywood Park, Inc., (1995-1996) (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) Meeting Minutes, (1996) (Box 16)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) Petition for Writ of Mandamus, (1998-2000) (Box 11)
    - CRDI (Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood) Response to Stadium DEIR (Draft Environmental Impact Report), (1995 Oct 19) (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Cultural Tourism in Goldstein Class: African American Neighborhoods by Halona Harrison, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 38)
    - David Beats Goliath: How Inglewood Defeated Wal-Mart (DVD recording), (2004) (Box 28)
    - Draft Petition of Mandamus - MJA, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - EIR (Environmental Impact Report) Process Review for Stadium, (1995) (Box 16)
    - Hollywood Park and Local 11 Neutrality Agreement, (1995) (Box 16)
    - Hollywood Park Casino Survey, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 47)
    - Hollywood Park Market Place, (1994 Sep 23) (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Hollywood Park Stadium Draft EIR (Environmental Impact Report), (1995 Sep 6) (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Hollywood Park Stadium Owner Participation Agreement, (1995 Oct 31) (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Hollywood Park, Inc. Settlement Agreements, (circa 1996) (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Inglewood Brochure, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Inglewood Quality Jobs Ordinance, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Inglewood Residents Demand Accountability flyer, (undated) (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Is Wal-Mart Good For America? as shown on PBS Frontline (VHS recording), (undated) (Box 35)
      Audiovisual materials will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - Local Hiring Ordinance City of Los Angeles, (1996) (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Surveys (2 files), (undated) (Box 12)
    - WAL * MART: The High Cost of Low Price [documentary] (DVD-R recording), (undated) (Box 28)
      Appears related to Coalition for Responsible Development in Inglewood. Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, please notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - Walmart Surveys, (2004) (Box 25)
  - Community Benefits Agreements
    - Adams La Brea (13 files), (2002-2003) (Box 11)
    - Amended Disposition and Development Agreement for Compton Card Club, (1995 Mar 21) (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Amended Disposition and Development Agreement for Compton Card Club, (1995 Apr 4) (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - CAUSE (Coalition for Accountability in the Universal Studios Expansion) Universal (2 files), (1998-1999) (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - CBI Briefing Meeting Presentation PowerPoint (on CD), (2005 Dec) (Box 28)
    - Community Benefits Agreements (DVD recording), (2006) (Box 28)
    - Disposition and Development Agreement for Compton Card Club, (1992 Dec 10) (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Greek Theater Living Wage (2 files), (1999-2000) (Box 10)
    - LASED (Los Angeles Sports and Entertainment District) Project (2 files), (undated) (Box 11)
    - Oaks Project (The), (circa 2000) (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Staples Living Wage (2 files), (1999) (Box 10)
  - Community Redevelopment Agency
    - CLA Report on Community Redevelopment Agency Motion by Mark Ridley Thomas, (1999 April 13) (Box 9)
    - Community Contacts, (2000) (Box 13)
    - Community Redevelopment, (2004) (Box 11)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Actions, (undated) (Box 9)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Background Information, (undated) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Living Wage, (1999) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Living Wage (11 files), (1999-2003) (Box 9)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Living Wage Community Present Martial, (1999) (Box 9)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Living Wage Policy, (1999) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Policy, (2000) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Policy, (2000) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Service Workers Policy (2 files), (1990-1991) (Box 9)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Tenant Incentive Program, (undated) (Box 8)
    - Community Redevelopment Agency Tenant Issue, (1999) (Box 8)
    - CRA (Community Redevelopment Agency) (5 files), (2000) (Box 14)
    - CRA (Community Redevelopment Agency) Campaign Originals, (1999) (Box 7)
    - CRA (Community Redevelopment Agency) Hearings, (2000 Mar 16) (Box 7)
    - CRA (Community Redevelopment Agency) Surveys (7 files), (1998) (Box 12)
    - Do's and Don'ts of Delegation Visit, (1999) (Box 9)
    - Enka Zucker: Community Redevelopment Agency issues, (1999) (Box 9)
    - Genesis Los Angeles Living Wage, (2000) (Box 7)
    - LACV (Los Angeles Convention and Visitors Bureau), (2000) (Box 11)
    - Local 11 Contract fight, (1998) (Box 11)
    - Media Strategy Community Redevelopment Agency, (1999) (Box 9)
    - North Hollywood Redevelopment Project (2 files), (circa 2000-2003) (Box 11)
    - Trizec Hahn, (2002) (Box 8)
  - Don't Waste L.A.
    - Blue & Green Alliance: The New Movement to Fight Poverty and Pollution(The) (CD), (undated) (Box 28)
  - Health Coverage
    - California Insurance, (1998-1999) (Box 18)
    - Catholic Healthcare West (2 files), (2000) (Box 10)
    - Coalition for Healthy Communities, (2002) (Box 10)
    - Contractors Employee Benefits Administration, Inc. insurance information, (undated) (Box 18)
    - Ensuring Health Coverage of the Publicly Insured, (1998 Sep 16) (Box 18)
    - Health Care Crisis, (2003-2004) (Box 18)
    - Health Policy Roundtable information packet, (2000 Apr) (Box 18)
    - Healthier Tomorrow Starts Today (A) handbook, (2003 Jun) (Box 18)
    - Insure the Uninsured Project information packet, (1998 Dec 16) (Box 18)
    - Insuring the Uninsured information, (1998 Dec 16) (Box 18)
    - Kaiser Permante - Small Business Advantage information packet, (undated) (Box 18)
    - No on Proposition KK, (2000) (Box 7)
    - Proposition 72, (2004) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 questions and answers (Spanish and English), (undated) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 results, (2004 Nov 8) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 Script, (undated) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 - SEIU 1877, (2004 Sep 28) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 Summary (Spanish and English), (2004-2007) (Box 18)
    - Proposition 72 survey, (undated) (Box 18)
    - Reaching 100 percent of California's Children with Affordable Health Insurance, (1998 Sep) (Box 18)
    - Senate Bill 2, (2003) (Box 18)
    - Senate Bill 2, Heath Care for Working Families calendar and sign-up, (2004 Nov) (Box 18)
  - Justice for Janitors
    - Justice for Janitors, (2000) (Box 11)
  - Long Beach Coalition for Good Jobs and a Healthy Community
    - Long Beach Coalition for Good Jobs and a Healthy Community (DVD recording), (undated) (Box 28)
    - Los Angeles Living Wage
      - ACORN Jobs and Living Wage Campaign, (1995) (Box 15)
      - Action Materials, (1996 Nov 26) (Box 15)
      - Action Plans, (1995 Dec 12) (Box 16)
      - AFL-CIO Living Wage Ordinance Resource List, (1997) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - AFL-CIO Research, (1997) (Box 12)
      - AFSOME Child Care Workers, (2001) (Box 13)
      - Airport Expansion, (1996-1998) (Box 5)
      - All Things Considered (audio cassette recording), (1998 Apr 15) (Box 35)
        Appears to be related to Los Angeles Living Wage. Audiovisual materials will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
      - Analysis of Living Wage Ordinance, (1997) (Box 15)
      - Argenbright, (2003) (Box 5)
      - Argenbright Security Materials, (1999) (Box 14)
      - Articles, (1996) (Box 16)
      - Audit notices, (1999) (Box 6)
      - Audit Results or Actions, (1999) (Box 6)
      - Background Reading - Ordinances, (2001) (Box 5)
      - Baltimore Living Wage Law, (1996) (Box 15)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) correspondence, (1998) (Box 6)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) Determinations, (1998) (Box 6)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) Report, (1998 Jan - Jun) (Box 7)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) Report to Personnel Continued, (1998 Aug 20) (Box 6)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) Site Visits and Contract Information, (1998) (Box 7)
      - BCA (Bureau of Contract Administration) tip sheets fax, (undated) (Box 7)
      - Big Box Ordinance, (2000) (Box 7)
      - Board of Referred Powers Meeting Notice, (1997) (Box 7)
      - Borders/Hotel, Employees, and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE), (2000) (Box 6)
      - Business Finance Center County of Los Angeles information packet (annotated), (undated) (Box 15)
        Appears to be related to the micro-business loan program.
      - Business Subsidies in Los Angeles: Getting a Return on Our Investment (Prepared by Stephanie Luce), (1996 Dec) (Box 15)
      - CAO Notice to Employers about Non-Retaliation, (1999) (Box 7)
      - CAO/CLA Report, (1997 Feb 17) (Box 15)
      - CAO/Implementation, (1999) (Box 7)
      - Case Law Files (7 files), (1992-1995) (Box 12)
        Washington Service Contractors; Boston Harbor; Golden State Case; Article Labor Cases.
      - Central Library, (1997) (Box 18)
      - Charter Reform, (1998) (Box 12)
      - Christmas Carol at City Hall Living Wage (A) Demonstration (Betacam SP recording), (1996 Dec 18) (Box 34)
      - City Attorney letter to DOL, (1996) (Box 14)
      - City Charter and Administration Code, (1995) (Box 15)
      - City Contractors Flyer, (undated) (Box 16)
      - City Council Correspondence, (1998) (Box 6)
      - City Council Delegation, (1998 Nov 6) (Box 6)
      - City Council Information, (1996) (Box 5)
      - City Council Member Meeting Minutes, (1996-1997) (Box 15)
      - City Letter Supporting Living Wage Training, (1998) (Box 9)
      - City's Declaration of Compliance Form, (1999) (Box 7)
      - Coalition Building Committee Strategy subcommittee, (1996) (Box 14)
      - Committee Recruitment Checklist, (circa 1996) (Box 14)
      - Community Mailing, (1995-1996) (Box 17, Folder 35)
      - Community Tourism Project, (1998) (Box 7)
      - Complaint forms files, completed by workers, (1999-2001) (Box 17, Folder 48)
      - Complaint forms in English and Spanish, (undated) (Box 13)
      - Compliance Reports for Rick Sanders, (1998 Nov 18) (Box 6)
      - Contact Lists, (1997) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Contact Sheets Kevin Mosley, (1996) (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Contractor Information (CAO), (1999) (Box 7)
      - Convention Center, (1996) (Box 18)
      - Copy of Employee Complaint Form, (undated) (Box 7)
      - Corporate Profits, (1997) (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Corporate Welfare Article, (1995 May 31) (Box 15)
      - Correspondence, (1996-1997) (Box 15)
      - Council Certificate of Appreciation to Joel Wachs, (1997) (Box 15)
      - Coverage of Los Angeles Living Wage Campaign (clippings, (1996) (Box 5)
      - Destination Los Angeles Magazine, (1993) (Box 9)
      - DOA Commissioners, (1998) (Box 5)
      - Donation to Living Wage Coalition, (1996) (Box 15)
      - Early Living Wage Materials LAANE, (undated) (Box 7)
      - Economic Development Corporation information packet, (1994) (Box 14)
      - Economic Impacts of Living Wage, (1996 Dec 9) (Box 16)
      - Economic Reports, (1996-1997) (Box 8)
      - Economist letters Living Wage, (1996-1997) (Box 14)
      - Empirical Analysis, Professor Richard Sanders, (1997) (Box 15)
      - Enforcement Hearing, (1998 Nov 18) (Box 6)
      - Ent. Interviews Notes, (1998) (Box 13)
      - Ethics Commission, (1996) (Box 13)
      - FAX/Mail Outs, (1996) (Box 14)
      - Final University of California Los Angeles Study, (1999) (Box 16)
      - Fire Commission, (1998) (Box 18)
      - Fred Assorted Notes and Articles, (1996) (Box 15)
      - Fred Seavey memos and notes, (1996) (Box 16)
      - Gary Mendoza File, (1995-1997) (Box 14)
      - General contract sheets and notes, (1996-1997) (Box 14)
      - General Services, (1997) (Box 18)
      - Golf Concessions (2 files), (1996-1997) (Box 18)
      - Greek Theater, (1999) (Box 18)
      - Greek Theater (5 files), (1999-2000) (Box 18)
      - Health Project Correspondence, (2001) (Box 5)
      - Heartland Agreement - letter of agreement between LA Living Wage Coalition and Chicago Institute on Urban Poverty, (1996 Jul 18) (Box 15)
      - Heartland Alliance, (1996 Aug) (Box 15)
      - Heartland Drafts, Notes and Correspondence, (1996) (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Higher Wage Impact on Employees, (1997) (Box 8)
      - Huntleigh workers survey (blank), (undated) (Box 13)
      - Huntley Workers, (undated) (Box 13)
      - Impact, (1996) (Box 13)
      - Jacob Marley Speech Flyer, (undated) (Box 15)
      - Jose Humberto Interview (member of Local 11) by Citlally Santana, (1996) (Box 15)
      - June Gibson, (2001) (Box 11)
      - June Gilson Fax Living Wage Coalition, (2001) (Box 13)
      - Kajima Golf Course, (1997) (Box 11)
      - Kopkind Colony, (1999) (Box 7)
      - LA Living Wage articles, (1997) (Box 5)
      - LA Living Wage Coalition (audio cassette recording), (1999 Nov 24) (Box 35)
      - Labor Law/Local/State/Fed, (2003) (Box 5)
      - Labor Peace Ordinance, (1999) (Box 18)
      - Labor Task Force Breakfast, (1996 Apr 3) (Box 14)
      - LAWA (Los Angeles World Airports) Rent Relief, (2002) (Box 6)
      - LAWA (Los Angeles World Airports) Service Contracts (SWRD and Living Wage Ordinance), (1998 Jan - Dec) (Box 6)
      - Lawyer contacts, (1997) (Box 14)
      - Lawyer support correspondence, (1997 Mar 14) (Box 14)
      - Lawyer support letters, (1997 Mar) (Box 14)
      - LAX airport Commissioner Letter, (2001) (Box 13)
      - LAX Airport Living Wage, (1999) (Box 6)
      - LAX General Information, (2000) (Box 5)
      - LAX Living Wage (7 files), (1997-2004) (Box 9)
      - LAX organizing project AFL-CIO, (1998) (Box 14)
      - LAX project AFL SIEU, (1999) (Box 14)
      - LAX project Correspondence and Notes, (1999) (Box 14)
      - LAX project materials, (1998) (Box 14)
      - LAX Project: Faxes, (1999) (Box 5)
      - LAX United, (1999) (Box 5)
      - Leaflets for the Living wage Campaign, (1996) (Box 15)
      - Leafletting/Monitoring Reports, (1998) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Letter from John Sweeny to Council Member Hernandez, (1997 Jan 22) (Box 14)
      - Letter to LA City Council Members, (circa 1996) (Box 15)
      - Letters From Workers (photocopies), (1997) (Box 14)
      - Letters to City Council, (1996) (Box 15)